Guide to the Listen to This: Crown Heights Oral History collection 2010.020
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Louis, Marie, 2010 April 28; 2010.020.027
  Marie Louis weaves her biographical details into her recollection of growing up in Brooklyn's Crown Heights neighborhood and her parents' emigrating from Haiti before her birth. She references her churches, schools, other local resources and a favorite bowling alley. Louis speaks of the sense of security and safety as a teenager and the diverse ethnicities and occasional tensions in the neighborhood. She describes her involvement in Brooklyn United for Innovative Local Development (BUILD), related to the Atlantic Yards Project and Crown Heights. Louis talks about being a community advocate and advises high school students on the importance of being inquisitive. Interview conducted by Ansie Montilus, Floyya Richardson, and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Barclays Center (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Carroll Street (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Eastern Parkway (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Haiti; Haitian Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Mayors |z New York (State) |z New York; Multiculturalism; Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn United for Innovative Local Development (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Louis, Marie; Prospect Heights School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Saint Gregory's Roman Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Lovell, Judith, 2010 March 4; 2010.020.028
  Judith M. Lovell was born in 1933 and raised in Brooklyn. Her early years were spent living on Putnam Avenue and Decatur Avenue in Brooklyn, and circa 1950, the family home became 1381 Union Street in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. Lovell commuted to Franklin K. Lane High School, where she majored in bookkeeping. She took her first job as an assistant bookkeeper in Manhattan's garment district. She met her husband, another Crown Heights resident, in 1953. They married at St. Gregory's Church in 1958, and parented two children (Judith C. Lovell is her daughter), living on Lincoln Place. Lovell balanced motherhood with a job as a school crossing guard on Nostrand Avenue. She also went to night school at Brooklyn College to study teaching. Lovell taught at P.S. 138, in a special education setting. At the time of the interview in 2010, she was volunteering as a literacy tutor at Brooklyn Public Library. Lovell and her family are longtime members of the Lincoln Civic Block Association and she attended St. Mark's and St. Gregory's churches.
  In the interview, Judith Lovell talks about moving from downtown Brooklyn to the neighborhood of Crown Heights. She cites the addresses of family residences then and in 2010 and recalls growing up in Crown Heights and commuting to her high school outside of the neighborhood. She relates the details of her first job as a bookkeeper, how she met her husband and their wedding. Lovell remembers her time as a school crossing guard on Nostrand Avenue, teaching at P.S. 138 and going to night school at Brooklyn College. She describes her current volunteer work as a literacy tutor at the Eastern Parkway Learning Center of the Brooklyn Public Library. Lovell remarks on the shifting demographics of her neighborhood, recalls a blackout that led to violence, and lists the family's participation in block parties, the Lincoln Civic Block Association, St. Mark's Church and St. Gregory's Church. She notes the change in Franklin Avenue over the years. Interview conducted by Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z New York; Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Nostrand Avenue (New York, N.Y.); Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn College; Brooklyn Public Library; Church of St. Mark (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Lincoln Civic Block Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Lovell, Judith; Saint Gregory's Roman Catholic Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Lumumba, Tonde, 2010 March 22; 2010.020.029
  Tonde Lumumba was born in St. Vincent in the West Indies in 1961. One of four children, he was raised by his father until he was asked to leave. He followed his mother's path and immigrated to the Brooklyn neighborhood of Prospect Heights at age sixteen. As an adult, Lumumba has lived in Bedford-Stuyvesant and Crown Heights, where he resided with his wife, three daughters and one son as of 2010. Lumumba owned and operated Imhotep's Health and Living Foods on Nostrand Avenue. Laying claim to being the oldest vegan restaurant in Brooklyn, the store was closed by 2013.
  In the interview, Tonde Lumumba observes the demographic change in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights, noting the arrival of more people of European ancestry. He discusses African art displayed in his store. Lumumba recalls the drug problem in the community during the late 1970s. He discusses his adult life in Brooklyn; moving from Bedford-Stuyvesant to Crown Heights and schools his four children have attended. Lumumba focuses on the history of his health food store and his own emergence as a health conscious eater and vegan. He briefly acknowledges the cultures with traditions in Crown Heights, particularly the West Indian celebration on Labor Day. Lumumba reflects on his arrival to Prospect Heights as an immigrant and his upbringing by a stern father in St. Vincent. He cites famous role models he has emulated, particularly as an activist and protester, and brings that modeling into how he lives positively in his community, even criticizing the lack of messaging in the West Indian Carnival. Interview conducted by Monica Parfait, Treverlyn Dehaarte, Quanaisha Phillips, Floyya Richardson, Ansie Montilus, and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Blacks |x Race identity; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 20th century; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions |y 20th century; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Caribbean Americans |z New York (State) |z New York |x Social life and customs; Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Ethnic neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Immigrants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Multiculturalism; Parades |z New York (State) |z New York; Rastafarians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Saint Vincent and the Grenadines; United States |x Emigration and immigration; Vegetarianism; West Indian Americans; Lumumba, Tonde; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
- Mark, Linda, 2010 March 17; 2010.020.030
  Linda Mark was born in 1945 in North Carolina. She was the second-oldest of seven children. She moved to New York City in 1965, was married from 1974 to 1978, and raised a son and daughter in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Bedford-Stuyvesant before moving to the nearby Crown Heights neighborhood in 1990. After working for the Department of Motor Vehicles, and Department of Labor, Mark was a postal worker until retiring. At the time of the interview in 2010, she was learning about becoming a nurse. Mark was a regular congregant of The Greater Bibleway Temple Apostolic Church.
  In the interview, Linda Mark describes the value of her church, the Greater Bibleway Temple. She reflects on her early impression of the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights and recalls experiencing the Blackout of 1977. Mark touches on life in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn in comparison to the more favorable environment of Crown Heights. She talks about her civil service jobs, culminating with the United States Postal Service, and how priorities in her retirement have mainly concerned improving her reading, traveling internationally, and considering another career in nursing. Mark relates some basic details about the family in which she grew up, when she married and the children she raised. She makes a couple comparisons concerning life in the South and life in New York City. A brief description of how she enjoys the West Indian Day Parade is followed by her views on Jews in Crown Heights and their values and holidays. Mark cites her neighbor and her church as sources of inspiration and community in her life. Interview conducted by Quanaisha Phillips, Treverlyn Dehaarte, and Alex Kelly.
  African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Catholic Church |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Christian life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Judaism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; North Carolina; Race relations |z United States; Segregation |z United States; Mark, Linda; United States Postal Service; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
- Mills, Randolph, 2010 April 7; 2010.020.031
  Randy Mills was born in 1930 in rural North Carolina. A grandson of a tobacco farmer, his family raised and farmed all of their own food. In his teens, he and his brother joined his already-settled parents in New York City. He got work there at his first job; selling at a fruit stand. As an adult, Mills married in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Bedford-Stuyvesant. The couple's first home at 363 New York Avenue was robbed, so they moved to St. John's Place and Underhill Avenue, and later Rogers Avenue and Crown Street. Mills is a father to two daughters and a son, and worked six or seven days a week as a truck driver. At the time of the interview in 2010, he was residing at the Marcus Garvey Nursing Home.
  In the interview, Randy Mills covers basic information about his family and places he has lived in the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Bedford-Stuyvesant, Crown Heights and Prospect Heights. He broadly describes the factors leading to the 1991 riot in Crown Heights and fondly remembers the excitement of the West Indian Carnival on past Labor Days. Mills recalls playing ball games as a younger man, which led to playing Dominoes in front of Brooklyn storefronts later in life. His recreation was disturbed by drug pushing and one shootout in the area. Mills' rural upbringing of growing food and playing with snakes is contrasted with coming to New York City and mistakenly stealing from a neighborhood fruit stand. He reflects on his marriage and offers relationship advice to young people. Interview conducted by Treverlyn Dehaarte, Floyya Richardson, and Alex Kelly.
  African Americans |x Relations with Jews; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Carnival |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crime |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Farms; Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; North Carolina; Nursing homes |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Race relations |z United States; Riots |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Street vendors |z New York (State) |z New York; Marcus Garvey Nursing Home (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Mills, Randolph; West Indian American Day Carnival Parade (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
- Oden, Eunice, 2010 April 21; 2010.020.032
  In 1942, Eunice Oden was born in North Carolina, where she grew up on a farm. At age eighteen, she arrived in New York City and shared an apartment with her sister. Her early years in Brooklyn were in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood, but she has lived in Crown Heights since January, 1969. She raised her son in those neighborhoods until his high school graduation in 1978. Initially, she worked in clothing factories and then held several jobs at a hospital for thirty-three years. She later worked for nursing homes and retired in 2007. Oden was a community activist, first taking note of prejudice in Brooklyn real estate and then being a Coordinator for Safety and Security at the 77th Precinct Executive Board. At the time of the interview in 2010, she was the president of her apartment building's tenant association.
  In the interview, Eunice Oden makes many observations about the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights where she has lived for four decades; including changes to parking and street traffic, intolerant real estate practices, abandoned buildings and shuttered businesses, the public's use of the Brooklyn Children's Museum and the Brower Park Library, the police behavior and presence from the 1990s to 2010, and the demographic shift of the neighborhood. She relates her experience of raising a son, with discipline and safety lessons, and looks at the larger picture of parenting, drugs, money, and influences on children. Oden recalls her experience as a child in North Carolina and contrasts the prevalent, overt racism there with the subversive racism in Brooklyn. She shares stories of at-risk youth running from police and an encounter with a rude salesperson at a store. Her interviewers prompt her to address civility between different generations on the streets and how a young person dealing with a stranger has changed over the years. Interview conducted by Treverlyn Dehaarte and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Courtesy |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Discrimination in housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Drug traffic |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hospitals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; North Carolina; Nursing homes |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Police |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Racism; Tenants' associations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.). Police Department; Oden, Eunice
- Pelham, Lillian, 2010 May 10; 2010.020.033
  Lillian Pelham was born in Brooklyn in 1932. In 1963, her brother, mother and daughter moved to a house on Sterling Place in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Since 1978, she has lived alone and stays active in her neighborhood. In the mid-1970s, she received an associate's degree in nursing at a community college and a bachelor's degree in Community Health and Counseling from St. Francis College. Her occupations have included nurse, entrepreneur and in particular, she served as the Health Resource Coordinator at George Wingate High School and provided group counseling at Samuel J. Tilden High School. After retiring, she wrote a self-help book, "Wisdom in the Air, Wisdom Everywhere." Pelham has three grandchildren.
  In the interview, Lillian Pelham is joined by her friend and neighbor Rosella La Fontaine, who is also a narrator in another oral history interview within this collection. Pelham talks about the experience of living on her block for almost five decades and seeing the demographics of residents change in that time. She shares a few details about her family and other homes on the block. The interview is largely about how she learned to be an author and how a book is published. She relates how she was inspired to write because of her work with at-risk youth in high schools. She concludes by giving advice to motivate and instill life goals for young people. Interview conducted by Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social conditions; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Illustration of books; Mental health services |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Older people |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Youth |x Conduct of life; City University of New York. Medgar Evers College; George W. Wingate High School; Pelham, Lillian L.; Samuel J. Tilden High School (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Phillip, Kevin, 2010 May 10; 2010.020.034
  Born in Trinidad in 1971, Kevin Phillip was raised by his parents in Brooklyn's Canarsie neighborhood and by his grandmother at Tivoli Towers, an apartment complex in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. He played basketball in high school but was also engaging in criminal business outside of classes. He dropped out of the eleventh grade to work, achieving a certificate in General Education Development (GED) later. Workplaces included Burger King, Waldbaum's grocery store and a messenger service. After taking a course at the Fashion Institute of Technology at twenty-one, he began creating and selling designs on t-shirts. In his early twenties, Phillip moved in with a friend in Crown Heights. An ex-convict, he established his own clothing retail shop, About Time Boutique, in 2008. Since the interview in 2010, the clothing store has closed. He went into business with his wife to open Candy Rush, a candy and ice cream shop, in 2011. That store closed in 2013. Phillip is the father to three boys and one girl and has spoken at public forums to encourage teens to become entrepreneurs.
  In the interview, Kevin Phillip speaks generally about trouble he caused as child while staying with his grandmother in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. He discusses factors that led him to drop out of high school, including entry-level jobs, a business that was on the wrong side of the law and a basketball injury. Phillip acknowledges the gentrification of Crown Heights, particularly Franklin Avenue. It was there, between Sterling and Park Places, where he established his first retail clothing shop. Phillip talks vaguely about his time in prison, but emphasizes the lessons he's learned. He talks about his effort to mentor to the youth community of Brooklyn, including a forum at Long Island University to introduce teens to the idea of small business ownership. Finally, Phillip talks about the challenging balance between family and business obligations. Interview conducted by Ansie Montilus, Monica Parfait and Alex Kelly.
  African American neighborhoods |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Businessmen |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Canarsie (New York, N.Y.); Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Ex-convicts |x Rehabilitation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fashion design |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Franklin Avenue (Brooklyn, N.Y.); Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Mentoring in business |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Work-life balance |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Youth |x Conduct of life; Fashion Institute of Technology (New York, N.Y.); Phillip, Kevin; Tivoli Towers (Brooklyn, N.Y.)
- Pierre, Lisa, 2010 March 24; 2010.020.035
  Lisa Pierre was born in 1960 at Brooklyn Jewish Hospital in the Crown Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. Born to parents who'd come up to New York City from Georgia and North Carolina, Pierre attended Public School 316, P.S. 42, I.S. 320 and Prospect Heights High School. She is dedicated to her church, Washington Temple Church of God in Christ, and has worked to provide day care and pre-school in the neighborhood. She is a community activist, with involvement in the Crow Hill Community Association and Parent Teacher Association. Pierre is mother to an adult son and two grown daughters.
  Lisa Pierre introduces herself in the interview as a dedicated congregant of Washington Temple Church of God in Christ. She recalls the four public schools she attended and the disruption of gang activity during the 1970s in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Crown Heights. She speaks about the child care services she provides at a nursery school and considers another career opportunity. Pierre remembers the games she played in the neighborhood of her youth and describes the surroundings then and now. She talks about her Crow Hill Community Association involvement, her pastor, Robert L. Madison, and the tradition of feet washing at the church. She looks back on her behavior as a teenager and what is required of a parent of teens in the current era. She also compares the offerings in the public schools that she experienced with what's been cut out of city schools since. She shares basic details on her family background and her birthplace. In conclusion, Pierre reminisces; about landmark movie theaters, hospitals and a bank; and recalls the Reverend Al Sharpton as young man at church functions. Interview conducted by Treverlyn Dehaarte and Alex Kelly.
  Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Community activists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Family life |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Games |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gangs |z New York (State) |z Kings Country; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Hospitals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Motion picture theaters |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nursery schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Parents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Pentecostal churches |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Public schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crow Hill Community Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Pierre, Lisa; Sharpton, Al; Washington Temple Church of God in Christ (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Porter, Evangeline, 2010 March 3; 2010.020.036